<clinical_study>
<study_id>
<org_name>
  QueensU
</org_name>
<org_full_name>
  Queen&apos;s University
</org_full_name>
<org_study_id>
  1
</org_study_id>
<secondary_id>
</secondary_id>
<nct_id>

</nct_id>
</study_id>
<brief_title>
<textblock>
  Efficacy of the Recovery Workbook as a Psychoeducational Tool for Facilitating Recovery
</textblock>
</brief_title>
<official_title>
<textblock>
  Efficacy of the Recovery Workbook as a Psychoeducational Tool for Facilitating Recovery in Persons With Severe and Persistent Mental Illness
</textblock>
</official_title>
<study_sponsor>
<lead_sponsor>
<agency>
  Queen&apos;s University
</agency>
</lead_sponsor>
</study_sponsor>
<oversight_info>
<regulatory_authority>
  Canada: Health Canada
</regulatory_authority>
</oversight_info>
<brief_summary>
<textblock>
The present study will determine if Spaniol and colleague&#8217;s (1994) Recovery Workbook group intervention is an effective clinical tool to move a person with SMI along in their journey of recovery. The primary outcome measurements of this study will be the participants&#8217; perceived level of empowerment, hope and optimism, knowledge of recovery, and life satisfaction. This kind of information would add to the current body of knowledge about how principles of recovery can be used in psychoeducational programs used by outpatient community mental health services. 
</textblock>
</brief_summary>
<detailed_descr>
<textblock>
  ABSTRACT:
Objective: Adopting the principles of recovery into the mental health field has been a growing area for discussion at many different levels of care. The present study will determine if Spaniol and colleague&#8217;s (1994) Recovery Workbook group intervention can be used as an effective clinical tool to move a person with a severe mental illness along in their journey of recovery. The primary outcome measurements of this study will be the participants&#8217; perceived level of empowerment, hope and optimism, knowledge of recovery, and life satisfaction. Method: The study will be a multicenter, prospective, single-blinded, randomized control trial. Sixty participants will be recruited from three Assertive Community Treatment Teams (ACTT) in Kingston, Ontario and individuals will be randomized to either the control or intervention arm of the study. The control arm of the study will receive their regular services from ACTT. The intervention arm will participate in a 10-week psychoeducational group program in addition to receiving their regular services from ACTT. Results: Analysis will be performed by intention to treat, based on total scores of four assessments which will be performed at the trial commencement and termination. 
</textblock>
</detailed_descr>
<status_block>
<status>
Not yet recruiting 
</status>
<date>
2006-05 
</date>
</status_block>
<start_date>
<date>
  2006-09
</date>
</start_date>
<end_date>
<date>
  2008-05
</date>
</end_date>
<last_follow_up_date>
<date>
</date>
</last_follow_up_date>
<phase_block>
<phase>
  Phase 3
</phase>
</phase_block>
<study_type>
  Interventional
</study_type>
<design>
  Treatment
</design>
<design>
  Randomized
</design>
<design>
  Single Blind
</design>
<design>
  Active Control
</design>
<design>
  Single Group Assignment
</design>
<design>
  Efficacy Study
</design>
<primary_outcome>

  Hope



</primary_outcome>
<primary_outcome>

  Empowerment



</primary_outcome>
<primary_outcome>

  Knowledge of Recovery



</primary_outcome>
<primary_outcome>

  Quality of life



</primary_outcome>





<condition>
  Mental Disorders
</condition>
<intervention>
<intervent_type>
Behavior 
</intervent_type>
<primary_name>
  Recovery Workbook Training (psychoeducational training)
</primary_name>




</intervention>
<eligibility>
<criteria>
<textblock>
  Inclusion Criteria:
   1.	Receive support from an Assertive Community Treatment Team.
  2.	Meet the DSM-IV diagnostic classification for schizophrenia, schizoaffective, schizophreniform, delusional disorder, or bipolar disorder.
  3.	Aged 18-55 years-old.  
  4.	Individuals agree to participate in the study after they have been informed of all the expected benefits and risks.
  5.	Neither substance misuse nor organic disorder judged to be the major cause of psychotic symptoms. 
 
 
  Exclusion Criteria:
  1.	Inability to give informed consent 
  2.	Diagnosis of dementia 
  3.	Significant head injury or other brain injury leading to cognitive impairment 
  4.	Mental retardation (premorbid IQ &lt; 65) 
  5.	Require an interpreter
</textblock>
</criteria>
<healthy_volunteers>
  Yes
</healthy_volunteers>
<gender>
  Both
</gender>
<minimum_age>
  18 Years
</minimum_age>
<maximum_age>
</maximum_age>
</eligibility>
<investigator>
<role>
  Principal Investigator
</role>
<name>
  Skye Barbic, BScOT
</name>
<affiliation>
<agency>
  Queen&apos;s University
</agency>
</affiliation>
</investigator>
<investigator>
<role>
  Principal Investigator
</role>
<name>
  Terry Krupa, PhD
</name>
<affiliation>
<agency>
  Queen&apos;s University
</agency>
</affiliation>
</investigator>
<contact>
<name>
  Skye P Barbic, BSc OT
</name>
<phone>
  613-549-3196
</phone>
<phone_ext>
</phone_ext>
<email>
  barbics@pccchealth.org
</email>
</contact>
<contact>
<name>
  Terry Krupa, PhD
</name>
<phone>
  613-533-6236
</phone>
<phone_ext>
</phone_ext>
<email>
  krupat@post.queensu.ca
</email>
</contact>
<location>
<facility>
<name>
  Queen&apos;s University
</name>
<address>
<city>
  Kingston
</city>
<state>
  Ontario
</state>
<zip>
  K7L 3N6
</zip>
<country>
  Canada
</country>
</address>
</facility>
<status>
  Not yet recruiting
</status>
<contact>
<name>
  Terry Krupa, PhD
</name>
<phone>
  (613) 533-6236
</phone>
<phone_ext>
</phone_ext>
<email>
  krupat@post.queensu.ca
</email>
</contact>
<contact>
<name>
  Sandra Olney, PhD
</name>
<phone>
  (613) 533-6102
</phone>
<phone_ext>
</phone_ext>
<email>
  olneys@post.queensu.ca
</email>
</contact>
</location>
<keyword>
  Recovery, Hope, Empowerment, Randomized Control Trial
</keyword>
<initial_release_date>
  2006-09-11
</initial_release_date>
<last_release_date>
2006-09-11 
</last_release_date>
</clinical_study>
